<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A word of information to them that need it briefly opening some most weighty passages of God dispensations among the sons of men, from the beginning, and insisting a little upon the state and condition of the nations, wherein they now stand, and particularly of England : for this end, that men may remember themselves, and turn unto the Lord, and seek to be delivered from the mysteries of iniquity, to walk with God in fellowship and communion : to which (as pertinent hereunto) is annexed, An addition concerning Lord-Bishops, and Common-prayer-book : with a tender admonition to those called priests, or ministers : and also, a loving exhortation to those that have separated from their superstitions / by W.T.</title>
            <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62901</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16928</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12599549</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12599549</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64127</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62901)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64127)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 676:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A word of information to them that need it briefly opening some most weighty passages of God dispensations among the sons of men, from the beginning, and insisting a little upon the state and condition of the nations, wherein they now stand, and particularly of England : for this end, that men may remember themselves, and turn unto the Lord, and seek to be delivered from the mysteries of iniquity, to walk with God in fellowship and communion : to which (as pertinent hereunto) is annexed, An addition concerning Lord-Bishops, and Common-prayer-book : with a tender admonition to those called priests, or ministers : and also, a loving exhortation to those that have separated from their superstitions / by W.T.</title>
                  <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Tomlinson. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64127:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64127:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Word of Information To Them that need it; Briefly opening ſome moſt weighty Paſſages of <hi>Gods Diſpenſations</hi> among the Sons of Men, from the beginning; And inſiſting a little upon the State and Condition of the Nations, wherein they now ſtand, and particularly of <hi>ENGLAND: For this end,</hi> That Men may remember themſelves, and turn unto the Lord; and ſeek to be delivered from the <hi>Myſteries of Iniquity,</hi> to walk with God in Fellowſhip and Communion. <hi>To which (as pertinent hereunto) is annexed,</hi> An <hi>ADDITION</hi> concerning LORD-BISHOPS, and COMMON-PRAYER-BOOK. With a Tender <hi>ADMONITION</hi> to thoſe called PRIESTS, or MINISTERS: And alſo, A <hi>Loving EXHORTATION</hi> to thoſe that have SEPARATED from their SUPERSTITIONS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle</hi> and <hi>Windmil,</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:64127:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64127:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>A Word of Information To Them that need it, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>GOD made Man at the firſt Upright and Innocent, and Pure and Holy, walking with him in his pure Nature, in perfect peace, and in boldneſs before him, having his Underſtanding filled with Light and Knowledge from the Lord, and his ſpirit poſſeſſed with the Spirit of the Lord. And therein he walked before the Lord in great liberty; only in one thing the Lord laid a Reſtraint upon him, <hi>Thou ſhalt not eat</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall ye touch it: for in the day thou eateſt thereof, dying thou ſhalt dye,</hi> Gen. 2.17. and 3.3.</p>
               <p>Now there was no way for that old enemy Satan, to rob Man of this happy, peaceable, innocent Condition, but by getting him out of the bounds where God had ſet him: for where no Law was, there could be no tranſgreſſion: and where no tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion was, death could not enter: for death came in upon Man by ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</p>
               <p>Therefore Satan that old Serpent, ſets upon Man here, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure and entice him, and flatter him into a tryal of that which God had forbidden him, by preſenting a pleaſurableneſs and profitableneſs in it.</p>
               <p>Man yeelding, the bound was broken that kept Man with the Lord, and kept out death and miſery. And now Sin enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. (that is, <hi>tranſgreſſing of Gods will and pleaſure</hi>) here with Sin, <hi>Death entered:</hi> and another ſpirit than before had poſſeſſion in man; even the ſpirit of the Serpent, that got in, and became Ruler in the Diſobedience.</p>
               <p>And now Death came over all in Man, and over all Men. The
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64127:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>flouriſhing ſtate of his ſoul in Righteouſneſs and Innocency, <hi>that dyed:</hi> a ſpirit of ſhame and fear, that covered him, and he now fled from the preſence of the Lord. And death alſo muſt now come upon his body, as well as upon his ſoul: for to duſt that muſt return. Thus dying Man dyed, according to the Word of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Yet now the Lord's mercies were not clean ſhut up from his Creature, which he had made ſo excellent, and given domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion unto over all other Creatures upon the Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.28. but he leaves a way open ſtill for Mans return unto himſelf, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a promiſed Seed, which was contrary to the ſeed of the Serpent; and ſhould bruiſe the Serpents head, that enticing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that leads to Diſobedience, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. So then here's no returning now for Man back again from Death to Life, but through that Seed that breaks the head of the winding diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Now in this faln ſtate Man lives, and begets Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and multiplies and repleniſhes the Earth. Thus the Earth is filled with Men and Women, begotten in the faln condition.</p>
               <p>And ſo as Men encreaſed and multiplied, Sin alſo that encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, until the Lord repented that he had made Man, and ſo drowned every living Creature wherein was the breath of life, that lived and moved upon the face of the Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5, 6, 7, 17.</p>
               <p>Yet in this ſinking dying condition, a Seed there was from the beginning that ſerved and obeyed the Lord, whoſe hearts were after him to return again unto him, who wrought works of Righteouſneſs, and walked with the Lord; as righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> and <hi>Seth,</hi> and holy <hi>Enoch,</hi> who was tranſlated that he ſhould not ſee death. And beſides theſe, a Generation that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon the Name of the Lord, and ſo were called <hi>the Sons of God,</hi> Gen. 4.26.</p>
               <p>Yet theſe alſo in proceſs of time wore out, after that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to corrupt themſelves, mingling themſelves with the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Men, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.2. So that in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> only <hi>Noah</hi> was found Righteous in his Generation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.8, 9. whom the Lord therefore (with his family) reſerved from the Flood, to plant the Earth with, after he had drowned the old world of the ungodly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.1.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64127:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Then again, after the Flood, as Men began to multiply, ſo they corrupted their wayes again before the Lord, ſo that in <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the eleventh from <hi>Noah,</hi> which was about three-hundred ſixty ſeven years after the Flood, God began <hi>to gather to himſelf a People again out of the reſt of the world,</hi> who ſhould bear his Name; and ſo he called <hi>Abraham</hi> out from his fathers houſe, and out of his own Country, to walk with him where he would appoinc him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.1.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Abraham</hi> was come out, then the Lord bleſſed him, and promiſed him to make of him a great Nation, and that he would bleſſe him that bleſſed <hi>Abraham,</hi> and curſe him that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Abraham.</hi> And ſaid furthermore to him; <hi>In thee ſhall all families of the Earth be bleſſed,</hi> Gen. 12.2, 3.</p>
               <p>So <hi>his Posterity in <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> were counted for the Lords Inheritance, and owned by him above all the World;</hi> and called <hi>his Son, his Firſt-born.</hi> And by that name he required them of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> when he ſent to deliver them out of the houſe of bondage, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.22, 23.</p>
               <p>Then when the Lord had delivered them by an out-ſtretched Arm from under <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Bondage, to lead them into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which he had promiſed to <hi>Abraham:</hi> When he had ſeparated them from <hi>Egypt,</hi> and brought them into the Wilderneſs of <hi>Sinai, <hi>There he gave them Statutes, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; a Miuiſtration of Laws, written in Tables of Stone.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of <hi>this Miniſtration <hi>Moſes</hi> was made the Mediator</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and them; and it was confirmed by many mighty Signs and Wonders. The Miracles done in <hi>Egypt</hi> by the hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> their paſſing therow the Red-Sea, as on dry land: <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his faſting forty dayes and forty nights: The terrible and dreadful Preſence of the Lord on the Mount; beſides his going before them in a Pillar of Cloud by Day, and in a Pillar of Fire by Night: And many other Signs and Wonders, all confirmed this Miniſtry given in the hand of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all this, and many moe great Signs and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which they ſaw, yet this People rebelled againſt the Lord, and did not walk with him with all their heart, but grieved him continually, as he complained of them by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by all his Prophets.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:64127:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>So that in the fulneſs of time God ſought out another People to bear his Name; and turned over the Promiſes made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to a ſpiritual Seed, Children of the Faith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> and brake down this partition-wall <hi>(ſtanding in outward Ordinances)</hi> which he had put between the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Centiles,</hi> becauſe they were all alike.</p>
               <p>And ſo out of both he gathered a People to himſelf; and made his Son the Captain of them; and gave to them <hi>another Miniſtry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Not a Miniſtration written in Tables of Stone,</hi> (as the firſt was, which was outwardly preſented before their eyes to look upon) <hi>But a Miniſtration which was inward, written in the Heart,</hi> by the Spirit of the living God.</p>
               <p>Of <hi>this Miniſtration, the Son was made Mediator;</hi> and ſo this Miniſtery was confirmed alſo by great Signs and Miracles which he did, in healing all manner of ſickneſſe and infirmity among the people, and raiſing of the dead, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>This Miniſtry was of a <hi>New Covenant,</hi> the Miniſtry of the Spirit into the Heart; and therefore it was needfull that the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator thereof ſhould be ſuch a one as could enter the ſpirit of the Creature, even <hi>the Lord that Spirit,</hi> who could ſtand at the door of the heart to miniſter, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.20.</p>
               <p>And ſo here came forth <hi>this great Myſtery,</hi> hid from Ages and Generations, namely, <hi>CHRIST in you the Hope of Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And under this Miniſtry the Apoſtle affirmed, <hi>That if any man have not the Spirit of CHRIST, he is none of his,</hi> Rom. 8.9. for that is his Miniſtry, to miniſter the Spirit; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Servants and Miniſters ſaid plainly, that they were <hi>not Miniſters of the Letter, but of the Spirit,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſee where all they are that partake not of the Spirit of Chriſt Jeſus, nor have any Teſtimony thereof in themſelves, witneſſing with their ſpirits that they are the Sons of God; nor feel the operation thereof in their own hearts, drawing them after Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, but deny it, and ſcoff at it in others, (that acknowledge the ſame, being guided and taught thereby) as uſually Perſecuters of Chriſtians have done in the Reign of Antichriſt.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:64127:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Now, after this Miniſtry came forth, here ariſes the <hi>Great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie</hi> alſo <hi>of Iniquity</hi> againſt it; namely, an Antichriſt againſt Chriſt in his Miniſtry, a carnal worldly ſpirit, clothing it ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Form of outward Obſervations, and yet ſetting it ſelf to keep down this Miniſtry of Chriſt Jeſus; even to quench and keep down this Spirit of Chriſt, with the Outward Form, void of the Power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Myſtery began to work in the Apoſtles dayes:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they called the Saints out from a Form without the Power, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p>But it could not grow to the height, till that which letted was taken out of the way.</p>
               <p>That which letted then, was ſomething that letted the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Form, which it grew up under; and that the Perſecuting <hi>Roman Emperors</hi> did a long while: for they perſecuted and killed ſuch as did but profeſs themſelves Chriſtians; ſo that under them the Myſterie could not come to its height, till they were taken out of the way. But then, after they were taken out of the way, and the form of Chriſtianity had ſcope, then it grew apace, till at laſt it was headed with an <hi>Univerſal Biſhop:</hi> which name the Pope took to himſelf, and ſo ſtill it grew, adding one Superſtition to another, and one Abomination to another, and prevailed greatly againſt the Saints of the Moſt High, <hi>Revel.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11. and 7.14. and 13.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>So here the holy City was troden under foot,</hi> by this Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Court, that was, the Gentiles gotten into an Outward Form, but came no nearer, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.2.</p>
               <p>And ſo the Myſterie prevailed, until it ſpread over <hi>many Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> that is, Peoples, Multitudes, Nations and Tongues, and reigned over the Kings of the Earth, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.1, 15, 18.</p>
               <p>And ſo here, that which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> make one great mark of their Church, namely, the Univerſality and Conſent of Nations; is plainly <hi>a great mark of the Myſterie of Iniquity,</hi> which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread multitudes of Nations for a long time, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.2. and 18.3.</p>
               <p>And under this <hi>Great Myſterie,</hi> the Portion of the Saints hath been, that they have been perſecuted and ſlain, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.6. and 16.5, 6. and in great Tribulation.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64127:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The VVHORE making the Nations believe that they were <hi>HERETICKS,</hi> and ſo killing them, becauſe they Diſſented from their Univerſal or Catholick Church, as they called it.</p>
               <p>Now here is one chief end of this Writing, to put men upon this Conſideration, <hi>Whether you be yet under this Mystery, or come from under it?</hi> Whether or no you have got victory over the Beaſt, over his Image, over his Mark, over the number of his Name; as the Saints do, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.2. Or you be yet drunk with the Wine of her Fornication? <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.2. Are you on the Perſecutors part, who are many; or on the Perſecuted part, who are few in compariſon? Are you drunk, or are you ſober? are you drunk with mens Inventions, and with blind Zeal, and Ignorance, and wrath to defend them; or are you come to ſobriety, to hear the voice of the Spirit, and of the Scriptures?</p>
               <p>Do not think that becauſe there was a breach from groſſe Popery in <hi>England</hi> formerly, that therefore you are out of the Myſtery: For you did but break off from her in ſome things, but the Life of that Myſtery is not yet ſlain among you, ſo long as you Perſecute, and tread under foot the Servants of the Lord; if you retain the Spirit of the Myſtery, that marks you for her Servants, reform as much as you will in your outward Obſervations.</p>
               <p>One thing I would have you conſider of;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether do you think that</hi> England <hi>did ſtep at one ſtep out of the depth of the Myſtery of Iniquity, back again into the pure Truth, as it was once delivered by Chriſt and his Holy Apoſtles?</hi> Conſider it well.</p>
               <p>Nay verily, there have been many ſtepping forward; and you who in outward appearance had removed one degree, yet you perſecuted all that ſaw more of the Myſtery than your ſelves, and ſeperated therefore from you: Whereby it is apparent, that the Spirit of the Myſtery was ſtill in you; And you proſecuted them with the names of <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> as the great Whore doth that Mother of Harlots; and your Mother therein; teaching you to call them <hi>Hereticks,</hi> that is, ſuch as ſeparate from the Truth, becauſe they ſeparated from you; making them odious by your Names of Blaſphemy which you fix upon them, that they might be hated of all men; and perſecuted by you without pitty. Such
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64127:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>meaſure have all they met withal, who have ſeen your Errour in Worſhip, or Doctrine, or Life, and have therefore witneſſed againſt it, ſo far as they ſaw.</p>
               <p>Thus it hath been with your Mother, your Church of <hi>England,</hi> and this hath been her manner of dealing with all that have ſtept out from her Errours. She hath retain'd the Spirit of her Mother, the Mother of Harlots in this her Fornication, and ſhe cannot clear her ſelf of it. The Impriſonments, Whippings, and Perſecutions of all thoſe <hi>She calls Hereticks,</hi> will jointly witneſſe againſt her, That the Spirit of the great Whore is yet retained in her, whoſe Mark is <hi>Blood.</hi> This Mark can ſhe not wipe off, ſince many have periſhed in Priſons, even of late years, through her Perſecution.</p>
               <p>But if any will contend againſt it, and defend her to be out from the Myſtery of Iniquity, and in the Truth, walking in the Truth as a True Church of Chriſt: We are able to prove to the contrary through the ſtrength of the Lord, even from her <hi>Teachers,</hi> from her <hi>Ordinances,</hi> and from <hi>your Lives</hi> and <hi>Converſations;</hi> all which demonſtrate you to be gone aſtray from the truth, as it was delivered by Chriſt, and his Holy Apoſtles; and are in the Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the great Whore; are yet drunk with the Wine thereof, and ſhall alſo drink of the wine of her wrath, if you repent not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your Teachers</hi> teach for hire, as the Falſe Prophets did of old, againſt which the True Prophets cryed out for ſo doing. <hi>Your Ordinances,</hi> none of them will abide the meaſuring line of the Scriptures: and ſo are but the outward Court, left out for the Gentiles, who tread the holy City under foot. <hi>Your lives</hi> are carnal; <hi>Your Converſations</hi> earthly, in the Luſts of the Fleſh, in the Luſts of the Eyes, in the pride of life; yea, <hi>Your Solemneſt Meetings</hi> are full of that ſin, for which God drowned the old VVorld, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.11. even <hi>full of Uiolence;</hi> witneſſe the violence done to any that come in, to ſpeak a ſober word of truth among you, and to inform you of your condition. Oh ſink down into your ſelves, and think, Is ſuch a Company the Spouſe of the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus? Is this his Church, his Body, the Pillar and Ground of Truth, were ſuch things abound?</p>
               <p>Take this VVord home to your hearts, and conſider it well; namely, that you are not got out of this Myſtery of Iniquity, till that from whence it grew be diſſolved. That you may underſtand
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64127:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>this ſaying, take notice, that the Myſtery of Iniquity grew from hence, even from the Earth unſubdued in Mans heart, which covering it ſelf with a Profeſſion of Truth outwardly, formed that Profeſſion, or Religion to its own Luſt or Liberty, that the Earth might ſtill be ſaved alive in Man, and live, and he enjoy his Luſts therein. And here in this ſtate ſtood <hi>Balaam,</hi> and in his way did the firſt Hereticks run in the Apoſtles times, loving the wages of <hi>Balaam</hi> for reward; and in his ſteps do they walk to this day: and thoſe that are one with them in the root and ground, though differing in outward appearance.</p>
               <p>For to this day its the ſame; The Earth ſtanding in Man's heart, and a Religion or Profeſſion raiſed up over that, forms a Myſtery of Iniquity, and begets an Antichriſt. It forms a Myſtery of Iniquity, or a myſt to hide Iniquity with; it raiſes a ſmoke out of the Pit of Mans heart, to blind the eyes of men with, and begets an Antichriſt, a Spirit of Perſecution, ſeeking to blaſt the True Spirit with Reproaches, which is Blaſphemy. And ſo under the name of Hereticks, and ſuch like, to ſlay them, to rid them out of the way, becauſe they ſtrike at the root, in which they live, by their holy Converſation; and by their chaſte Mind, to the Wiſdom of the Lord; abhorring the ſmoak and myſt of mens deviſings, which ariſes out of mans heart.</p>
               <p>More particularly to deal with you, and to ſet before you your own ſtate or ſtanding, let us compare you a little with the Primitive Times, and ſee whether you anſwer to the Church then, or to the World which hated it, and perſecuted it.</p>
               <p>The Church of Chriſt then ſuffered by the World, being diſtinct from the World, called out of it, and therefore hated by them of the World, <hi>Ye ſuffered joyfully the ſpoyling of your goods,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to the Church) <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32, 33, 34. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.14, 15, 16. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.4. So then in that time there was the Haters and the Hated; the Spoilers and the Spoiled; the Abuſers and the Abuſed; the VVolves devouring, and the Sheep devoured.</p>
               <p>Now compare your Church with them. Are you the Sufferers, or thoſe that put others to Suffering for Righteouſneſs ſake? Did not the people of tender Conſcience who could not worſhip God after the Traditions of men, ſuffer under your Church, both formerly when the Antichriſtian <hi>Lording Biſhops</hi> ruled it, and ſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64127:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>fled, ſome to <hi>New-England,</hi> and others to other Places? And ſinc they were put down, ſtill you have been the ſame. What haling, pulling puſhing, abuſing of people hath been in your Congregations, and by them of your Congregations! what beating in your Synagogues, ſtoning in your Streets, ſtocking, whipping, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, perſecuting, ſpoyling of goods, <hi>&amp;c!</hi> And nowthat thoſe Antichriſtian Prelates are coming in again, you are ſtill the ſame, and the ſame meaſure hath been met withall from ſome of you already.</p>
               <p>If any ſay, <hi>Thoſe that did ſo, or do ſo, are but the Rude Rabble, and are not to be counted for our Church.</hi> I Anſwer, Theſe things have been done among you, and by them that are of you unreſtrained. If by the Rude Rabble, then behold the Rude Rabble are the ſtrongeſt part of your Church, if they do ſuch things, and you cannot reſtrain them from that violence. If you ſay. <hi>Yea, we could have hindered them if we would, but we did not, becauſe we look upon thoſe they abuſed, as Seducers.</hi> Anſw. Then ſee, you conſented to their violence, and ſo made your ſelves Partakers with them; as <hi>Saul</hi> did, when he conſented to them that ſtoned <hi>Stephen.</hi> But ſay you, <hi>They were Seducers, they were Hereticks that were abuſed, and our Miniſters ſpake againſt them.</hi> I Anſwer, So did they ſtone <hi>Steven,</hi> as a Seducer, and all the violence done to them that feared the Lord, was in ſuch like thoughts of them; they thought they were Seducers, and their Miniſters ſpake againſt them. But where did ever the true Church uſe violence even to Seducers and Hereticks? Conſider that. They ſuffered violence themſelves, but never uſed violence to others. So ſee your ſelves now on what part you ſtand: For whatever they be that you uſe violence to for conſcience ſake, whether they be in the Truth, or be Seducers; yet your violence to them declares you not to be the true Church, but to be the World, where the perſecution is found. You are on the Perſecuters part, not on the Perſecuted: You are not they that the VVorld hates, but you are they that do hate others for Conſcience ſake; ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid they Themſelves were before Converſion, <hi>hatefull and hating one another,</hi> Titus 3.3. and ſo others ſuffer under you for Conſcience ſake, even thoſe againſt whom you cannot juſtly complain, for any wrong done to you by them: and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64127:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo they ſuffer innocently as to you, although they ſhould be Seducers. So ſee your ſelves now, That your Church reſembles not the Church of Chriſt in the Primitive time: but You fully reſemble the World, that then abuſed the Saints, and Servants of the Lord. And for your counting and calling them Hereticks, and Seducers that ſuffer under You and your Miniſters: This makes the Sufferers more reſemble the true Church, to be called and counted Seducers by a violent Generation; for ſo were the Saints accounted in the Primitive times by a like Generation as you are. And whereas ſome may ſay, <hi>Its but the rude Rable that uſe violence.</hi> I anſwer, Its manifeſtly proved by their Actions, that not only they, but their Teachers alſo are guilty of the ſame violence, partly by ſtirring up the Rude People, and encouraging them thereunto; and partly alſo by exerciſing it with their own hands, as ſome of them have done; and partly alſo by unjuſt proceedings, through Covetouſneſſe and Deſire of filthy Lucre, mingled with a wrathfull, raging, implacable, cruel, unjuſt, and unmercifull Spirit, having ſpoiled Families, making a prey of their Goods. Judg in your ſelves, Is this like the Saints in the Primitive Times, or like the World? Is this like the Sheep, or like the Wolves that devour? Again your principal men in many of your Congregations, have had a deep hand in theſe Actions of Violence, even your JUSTICES, and other OFFICERS among you, who have ſometimes encouraged the Rude Rabble in their Violence againſt the Innocent, and oftentimes even themſelves buffetted and abuſed, and whipped and ſtocked, and thruſt out from among them, thoſe that harmed them not; yea often have ſent them to Priſon, and there moſt cruelly entreated them, during their pleaſure, and that without any juſt crime, or breach of any of their Lawes many times; even thus have they dealt to ſuch as have wronged no man, but only ſought to informe you of your dangerous ſtate in which you ſtand, as enemies to God, and his Truth, and wayes; wading in Superſtitious Inventions, which will not profit you. For this thing have you thus abuſed them: and you are all guilty from top to toe, from higheſt to loweſt, who have conſented in your hearts to the violence done. So ſee your ſtate where you ſtand: See by your Antipathy to ſuch as fear the Lord, and by your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64127:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Agreement with the world, where you are. You are yet even of the world, though you be counted a Church. You have the <hi>Name,</hi> but not the <hi>Thing:</hi> You have not the Spirit and Life of the Saints: And ſo we have good reaſon to ſeparate from you, and to come out from amongſt you, as we are commanded by the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17, 18. <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.4. For, <hi>your Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon holds better with the Synagogues of the Jews, than with the Churches of Chriſt:</hi> and yet you fall ſhort of them alſo.</p>
               <p>In them there was Haling, Pulling, Beating, Thruſting forth, Abuſing, uſing Violence; as you may read in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles. And ſo here is your pattern, even the Synagogues of the <hi>Jews,</hi> where the Servants of the Lord were abuſed, for hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the Truth. But herein you excel thoſe Synagogues in Wickedneſs, and fall ſhort of them in Moderation: In that they gave liberty to men to ſpeak among them, and to reaſon and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute among them; as you may read, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.14, 15. and <hi>Act.</hi> 17.1, 2. and in many other places in that Book: Where you may read what liberty they gave unto the Apoſtles and Saints in thoſe times; though they came with a new Doctrine to them, which overturned all their former ſtate of a Church: yet did they not abuſe or moleſt them, until they heard Doctrine delivered which they accounted dangerous and erroneous: But you with open mouth and violence are ready to ſwallow men up before they can well ſpeak a ſentence out to be underſtood; yea, though you your ſelves cannot deny the truth of that which is ſpoken. So that you fall far ſhort of the <hi>Jews</hi> Synagogues in moderation and ſobriety: even ſhort of thoſe whom you your ſelves count Perſecuters of the true Church. How ſhould you then be the true Church? Your Violence breaks out, before you underſtand wherefore; ſo did not theirs: So you are worſe than they. And this is your ſtate and condition. So ſee your ſelves herein; and ſee your Miniſters what they are that encourage you herein.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Old World</hi> which was deſtroyed by water, and <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> which were deſtroyed by fire, are revived in your Streets and Aſſemblies; yea, in your ſolemn Aſſemblies, in the point of Violence, which was a principal thing topping up all their wickedneſs, for which they were deſtroyed. The <hi>Old World</hi> was full of Violence, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.11. and ſo was <hi>Sodom</hi> unto ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64127:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>And ſo are your Streets and Synagogues; and therefore ſpiritually you are more like <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> where our Lord is crucified, than to the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Therefore take not your ſelves any longer to be that you are not; nor blaſpheme the Name of Chriſt any longer, by calling your ſelves his Church, while you live in ſuch wickedneſs; but rather fear his Indigation, leſt that, or ſome like judgment come upon you, which came upon thoſe who lived in Violence as you do. The Church of Chriſt is pure; And whoever gets the name, and yet lives in impurity, ſhall be kept out from entring into the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> which is now coming down from God out of Heaven; not ſeen with outward eyes, nor known to carnal hearts, nor entred into by the unclean; and yet her gates ſtand open day and night.</p>
               <p>But to keep lower to your capacity. In the Primitive times the Church was patient under their ſufferings, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.4. Are you ſo? Or are not they rather found ſuch, who ſuffer by you? Do not ye caſt out hard ſpeeches with your Violence againſt them that are found in the like patient ſuffering with the Saints in the Primitive times? So ſee and judge impartially: Is it you that reſemble the Church of Chriſt; or is it thoſe that you rage againſt that reſembles it?</p>
               <p>Again, Is not your Church made up of ſuch perſons as fear not God, ungodly men and women, Sweaters, Drunkards, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpeakers, Revilers of thoſe that are good, Proud and haughty and high-minded Perſons, glorying in Apparrel and gay clothing, other than what the Apoſtles of our Lord approved of; conceited perſons, yet dark and ignorant in the things of God, men that take pleaſure in Wantonneſs and Vanity, and Paſtimes <hi>(as they call them)</hi> who count fooliſh talking and jeſting, an ornament to their ſpeech, and grace to their behaviour, being paſt feeling in themſelves of the things that diſpleaſe God, and quench the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; men that ſavour not the things of God, nor have any pleaſure and delight in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, to whom it's a burden even to hear of things ſpiritual, that belong to the Kingdom of God, out of whoſe communication ſpiritual things are ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; ſo that it's uncouth and diſtaſtful to them to confer of the things of the Kingdom of God before them, and eſpecially when
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64127:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>they are feeding themſelves without fear upon the good creatures of God. Others are carnally minded, worldly minded, having their ſpirits eaten up with the Thoughts of the world, and Cares of the world, and Love of the world, and Honour of the world, and Luſts of the world; Covetous perſons, who dare lie one to another for their advantage, and over-reach one another for the greedineſs of gain; Promiſe-breakers, who will promiſe to one another, and frequently fail one another in their Promiſes; ſo that you dare hardly truſt one another.</p>
               <p>Is not your Church now made up of theſe and ſuch like per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, guilty of theſe and ſuch like wickedneſſes? Pick out all that are ſuch (in your thoughts) and ſee how many will be left behind. If any be, they are called out by the Lord, who ſaith, <hi>Come out of her my People, leſt you partake of her ſins, and ſo partake of her plagues.</hi> To be ſuperſtitious, though never ſo much in the traditions of men, it will not keep off the wrath of God from ſuch workers of Iniquity. And you have nothing elſe <hi>(that's peculiar to your ſelves in your Church-ſtate)</hi> to be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of: as hath been manifeſted in another Writtng, called, <hi>A Reproof to your Prieſts, or Miniſters, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now conſider in the fear of God, as if you were to give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of your judgment in that thing before him, and before his holy Angels; Are ſuch as theſe, think you, ſuch (I ſay) as are reckoned up, ſuch as your Church is made up of; Are ſuch (I ſay) the Church of Chriſt? Are theſe the Church in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſanctified by his Spirit? Are theſe the body of Chriſt? Are theſe the pillar and ground of Truth? For the true Church of Chriſt is all theſe. If ſuch perſons as you conſiſt of be the Church, then tell me who are the World? Oh how apparent it is what you are! and yet have you Teachers heaped up to your ſelves after your own luſts, anſwerable thereunto, who ſew pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows under your elbows, and bear up your name for <hi>CHRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIANS</hi> in this State.</p>
               <p>If any one oppoſe the things here written, I ſhall more cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to him with theſe <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AERIES</hi> following, which I require him to anſwer in himſelf clearly without dawbing, leſt he ſtop his own way, and the way of others from returning and looking after the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:64127:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <list>
                  <item>Quaery. 1. <hi>Whether there be ſuch a thing as a Cup of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication over-ſpreading the Nations ſince the dayes of Chriſt, wherewith the Nations are made drunk? according to</hi> Revel. 19.2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.23.</item>
                  <item>Quaer. 2. <hi>Whether there be ſuch a thing as a great Whore that ſitteth upon many Waters, that is, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Multitudes, Nations and Tongues? according to</hi> Revel. 17.1, 15.</item>
                  <item>Quaer. 3. <hi>Whether ſhe hath not prevailed to corrupt the Earth with her Fornication, according to</hi> Revel. 19.2. <hi>even to give to all Nations to drink of the Wine of the Wrath of her Fornication,</hi> Chap. 14.8. and 18.3. <hi>and ſo to make them drunk therewith,</hi> Revel. 17.2. <hi>Yea, and prevailed over the Kings of the Earth alſo, to make them drink of the ſame Cup?</hi> Revel. 17.2. Chap. 18.3.</item>
                  <item>Quaer. 4. <hi>Whether this great Whore ſhall not be judged from the Lord, and burnt with fire? according to</hi> Revel. 18.8.</item>
                  <item>Quaer. 5. <hi>Whether ſhall not they that partake of her ſins, partake of her plagues? according to</hi> Rev. 18.4.</item>
                  <item>Quaer. 6. <hi>Whether cannot this Whore be known to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Lord, ſeeing the Book of the</hi> Revelations <hi>which declares her, was written for this end, to ſhew unto his Servants things which were to come to paſſe?</hi> Revel. 4.1. &amp; Ch. 1.1.</item>
                  <item>
                     <p>Quaer. 7. <hi>Whether it doth not highly concern us all to be able to know her, and the Cup of her Fornications, that ſo vve may avoid her plagues, by coming out of her?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>More particularly thus: <hi>Whether it doth not highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern us all to know, <hi>What this Whore is?</hi> What her <hi>golden Cup of Fornication is?</hi> and by <hi>what means ſhe reacheth it forth unto the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64127:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Earth,</hi> to make all Nations drunk there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith, that ſo vve may take heed of it, and ſeek to be cleared from it?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>If theſe <hi>QVAERIES</hi> be yeilded unto; then in the next place (for diſcovering a little further what this Whore and her Fornication is) it is <hi>Quaeried;</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether ſhe be not called</hi> WHORE <hi>for departing from the Bed of Christ to another husband?</hi> More plainly thus: <hi>for departing from being chaſte to the Counſels of Chriſt, and from lying down in his Wiſdom; to let in the Wiſdom of the fleſh, and ſubmit to the Inventions of man, inſtead of Chriſts Counſels? Whether her Whoredom doth not lye herein principally, according as the Iſraelites formerly were charged with Whoredom for the like?</hi> Ezek. 6.9.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>And whether this be not the golden Cup of her Fornication, wherewith ſhe hath overcome the Nations, and made them drunk: namely,</hi> A Pack of mens Inventions and Traditions, <hi>gallantly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the fleſhly mind, and decently ordered together, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and upheld with great reverence (as to outward appearance, and as all Idols have been upheld with a like reverent Solemnity) ſo that therewith ſhe hath taken the minds of the Inhabiters of the Earth ſo generally, and the Kings of the Earth alſo; and hath ſubjected them to thoſe Inventions, and overcome their minds to fall under them, as under the Counſels and Ordinances of the Lord; and with that conceit hath made them drunk: ſo that they being intoxicated with that conceit, like drunken men, will hear no reaſon againſt them, though evident from the Scriptures; but even like Drunkards, fight and quarrel, and are ready to buffet, and kill and ſlay them, that ſhall not ſubmit to the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions with them, and call them, and count them Ordinances of God as they do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let any one that oppoſes this, ſhew what the general Cup of Fornication is ſince the dayes of Chriſt, if this be not it: and let him ſhew how his Cup will anſwer the things ſpoken of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64127:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the <hi>Revelation</hi> concerning it. Let him ſhew another Cup ſo general, wherewith the Nations have been made drunk, according to what is ſaid, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.8. and 17.2. and 18.3, 23. and 19.2.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the Cup of Fornication be thus underſtood, then it is Quaeried. <hi>Whether the <hi>means by which</hi> ſhe reacheth forth this Cup to the Inhabiters of the Earth ſo generally, be not by their</hi> National Miniſtries? <hi>Whether any other way is found large enough and adaequate to the work; namely, to effect a general Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to mens Inventions, and to ſubject the minds of men ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to own Inventions and Traditions of men, for Ordinances of God; and to keep them reſting under that Fornication, but Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistries that may go over them all?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Whether the Nations be willing to lye down under, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to; or have layen down under, and ſubmitted to the Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of any Miniſtries, but them they own, and pay Wages to? If they be deceived, as the Scripture witneſſes they are,</hi> Rev. 18.23. <hi>Then is it not from their own Miniſtries, ſeeing they will not receive Truths nor Deceits neither from any other, but fight againſt them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now thou who haſt read theſe things, and thereby receiveſt any light into thine underſtanding; take heed henceforth of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling the Servants of the Lord, who in his fear follow the Lamb whitherſoever he goes, leading them out of <hi>the Myſtery of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquity</hi> by ſteps, as they have been able to bear: Who have tryed their wayes by the Word of Truth, and tryed alſo the falſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable wayes of mens Traditions and Inventions. Take heed, I ſay, of ſpeaking evil of the things thou underſtands not: and if thou haſt been guilty hereof formerly, repent of that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and pray to the Lord to forgive the thoughts of thine heart, and the hard ſpeeches of thy mouth, uttered againſt the wayes of Truth in the time of thy Ignorance.</p>
               <p>And reſt not until thou haſt got out of thoſe Miſts which have riſen out of the bottomleſs Pit, and which have darkened the Sun in the firmament; that is, the pure ſhining of the Light into the Conſcience. Haſte, haſte out of that which the Wrath and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64127:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Indignation of the Lord muſt come upon, and fly to him in the humility of thy ſoul, repenting of thy errour, and blindneſs, and hypocriſie, and evil ſtate and courſe of life thou haſt been in, and come down to be guided and led of that pure Light which leads to Eternal Life, and ſo to come to the Covenant of God, the New Covenant, which all are in that are owned by him. For this is my Covenant, ſaith the Lord, <hi>In thoſe dayes, I will write my Laws in their minds, and put them in their hearts.</hi> And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is not come into this Covenant, he is not owned of God: For all his, <hi>from the leaſt to the greateſt, ſhall all be taught of God,</hi> by his Spirit. And therefore ſaith the Apoſtle plainly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>If any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his. Now this is that which</hi> The ANTICHRIST <hi>by the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity, hath held you off from:</hi> for his working hath been againſt the New Covenant, which we now clearly ſee, and by what means he doth it, (eternal praiſes be given to our heavenly Father, who hath made known his wiles and deceivings) For it hath been with a golden <hi>Cup,</hi> that the <hi>Anti-Anointing,</hi> or <hi>Anti-Chriſt</hi> hath deceived the Naitons; even a fine ſpun outward Form of Religion, of ſome kind or other; So keeping their minds ſtill outward from that New Covenant; keeping them buſie with this Form or that Form outward, that they might never come to mind God in the way of his <hi>Covenant.</hi> For whereas the <hi>New Covenant</hi> comprehends all the Worſhip of God inwardly in it ſelf; Circumciſion inward, Baptiſm inward, <hi>viz.</hi> the anſwer of a good Conſcience to God, which is that that ſaves; Temple in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Houſe of Prayer inward, Worſhip inward in Spirit, and in Truth. Contrariwiſe, <hi>The Myſtery of Iniquity hath kept mens minds ſtill outward,</hi> and pleaſed the carnal ſpirit with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Outward Obſervations; thereby reſting it in them, by bleſſing them in their diligent Obſervation thereof; So that they have not been ſtirred up to ſeek after the knowledge of God in themſelves, and to feel the Communion and Fellowſhip inwardly with him in the way of his <hi>New Covenant</hi> in the Spirit, which <hi>CHRIST</hi> was made the Mediator of. And ſo about theſe Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Forms and Ordinances (ſo called) they fight and quarrel, and ſeek to kill and deſtroy, and ſo ſtill are kept in the murdering ſpirit.) And ſo lot this be <hi>A Sign</hi> unto you, to let you know
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64127:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>in what State that Spirit holds you, that makes you zealous for outward formes. Is it not in the murthering State where <hi>Cain</hi> was? and yet you ſee not his wiles; for he that murthers is the ſame from the beginning. In the New Covenant its otherwiſe: for there's a Spirit that delights to ſeek and ſave that which is loſt; and that is of God, and conformable to the Image of his Son; To whom be Glory and Honour for ever, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>An ADDITION concerning</hi> LORD-BISHOPS.</head>
               <p>Let the Light in every ones Conſcience (who have any acquaintance with the Scriptures) judge, Whether Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt allowed of that Lordſhip and Dominion, which thoſe called <hi>Lord-Biſhops</hi> take upon them, or exerciſe; when as he reproved the very firſt appearance of ſuch a thing among his Diſciples, read <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.25, 26. <hi>Mark</hi> 10.42, 43. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.25, 26. ſaith he, <hi>The Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe Dominion over them, and they that are great exerciſe Authority upon them; <hi>But it ſhall not be ſo among you:</hi>
                  </hi> but <hi>whoſoever will be great</hi> (minde, thats the thing he reproves) <hi>whoſoever will be great <hi>let him be your Miniſter,</hi>
                  </hi> that is, <hi>ſervant</hi> (and then he repeats it over again in other words) <hi>And whoſoever will be chief among you, let him be your Servant.</hi> And in <hi>Luke</hi> its thus expreſt; <hi>Let him be as a younger.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, carry quite contrary to ſuch a one in the thing that he would have. Whereas he affects Greatneſs, carry to him as a Servant, and as a Younger; give him not the honour of an Elder.</p>
               <p>Now where's their Obedience to Chriſt, who dare take upon them ſuch a thing which he hath ſo plainly forbidden? Yea, and <hi>forbidden others alſo to receive them as ſuch,</hi> if any will be ſo bold as to exalt themſelves among them, and become great. For faith our Lord, If any will get up, and be <hi>great among you, let him be your ſervant, and as a younger.</hi> Wherein the words of Chriſt is implyed; That Dominion and Greatneſſe cannot grow up among them, except they concurre with him that ſeeks it, and give it to him. Therefore as laying a charge of keeping down ſuch a ſpirit, upon the reſt of his Diſciples, he bids them, not to concurre and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64127:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſent to ſuch a thing, nor to give that greatneſſe to any of his Diſciples among them, if they ſhould ſeek it; but to carry to ſuch, <hi>as to a Younger,</hi> and not as to an Elder; and to let him be <hi>as one that ſerves,</hi> and not as one to Lord it, and Rule, and have Dominion. And ſo to keep down that ſpirit, that it may <hi>not be among You as it is among the Gentiles,</hi> that know not me to be the one Lord. Honour is in him that gives it; If you give it not they cannot have it.</p>
               <p>To open the thing a little further, for the ſimplicity's ſake, that is in ſome who think, That becauſe there is the <hi>name Biſhop</hi> in Scripture, that therefore ſuch Biſhops as have the Name now in theſe dayes, have their Authority from Scripture. To ſuch I ſay, Minde but the Scriptures well, and you will find that the <hi>Name Biſhop</hi> was not given to one that Lorded it over the reſt; but to the ſeveral Paſtors, or Teachers, or feeders of the Flock of Chriſt, read <hi>Act.</hi> 20.17, and ſo on to the 28, and 35. The place is ſo tranſlated that it may be you will diſcern little in the bare reading of it. I ſhall therefore open it a little plainly, according to the Letter of it; not by giving you another meaning, or Interpretation, then what it ſayes, but by letting you ſee what it ſayes.</p>
               <p>In the 17 Verſe its ſaid, that <hi>Paul ſent from Miletus to Epheſus, to call the Elders of the Church of Epheſus.</hi> When they were come, he puts them in minde after what manner he had been among them at all ſeaſons, ſerving the Lord in all humility of minde, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo ſets his own Holy Converſation, in which he had lived among them, as an Example freſh before their eyes, to have it in remembrance: and tells them, that they ſhould ſee his face no more: And ſo exhorts them, ſaying, <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, and to all the Flock over which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you OVERSEERS, to feed the Church of Chriſt, which he hath purchaſed with his own blood.</hi> That Word that may yet keep the thing a little dark to you, is the word <hi>OVERSEERS,</hi> which ſhould be tranſlated <hi>BISHOPS, (if that word be to be uſed at all in Scripture)</hi> For its the ſame here which is in other places of Scripture, where you read the word <hi>Biſhop,</hi> namely <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, EPISCOPOS, <hi>Biſhops.</hi> And why it ſhould be tranſlated <hi>OVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEERS</hi> here, and <hi>BISHOPS</hi> in other places, I know not, except to keep the people in ignorance. For, tranſlare it <hi>Biſhops</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64127:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>here, and then too great a light (might they think) would be let in to the people to fee what ones the <hi>Biſhops</hi> formerly were. For here the people might ſee, <hi>There were many of them in one Tongregation,</hi> or, at leaſt, more then one here in this Congregation at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which was but a City, and the Flock or Congregation in which the Holy Ghoſt ſet them <hi>Biſhops,</hi> was but a Company of people gathered out from the reſt of that City, (as you may read in the 19. Ch. where you may ſee the very beginning of this Church,) And yet was there <hi>ſeverall Biſhops in that Company,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle,) <hi>and to all the flock in which the holy Ghoſt hath ſet you Biſhops,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to feed the Church of God</hi> (or in plain Engliſh) <hi>to feed the call'd out Flock of God,</hi> which he hath obtained by his own blood: For ſo was the Church, It was a Flock call'd out from among the World; and ſo the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſounds.</p>
               <p>So then, in this Church at <hi>Epheſus</hi> (which was but one Company or Flock, lately gathered out of the world,) <hi>In this one Flock were ſet Biſhops more then one:</hi> and there they were ſet to feed them, and watch over them, which were therefore call'd <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Watchers over,</hi> which is <hi>here tranſlated OVERSEERS, but in other places of Scripture its tranſlated BISHOPS.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, if you will have the word OVERSEERS here uſed, as it is in the Tranſlation; then do but uſe the ſame word in all other places of Scripture where you find the word <hi>Biſhop</hi> (as it is the ſame in the Greek which you call the originall,) and then not ſo much as the <hi>Word BISHOP</hi> would be found in the Scriptures. Or if you had rather retain the word <hi>Biſhop,</hi> then uſe it in this place (namely <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28.) as well as in other Places: And then you may plainly ſee, that they were <hi>no Lords,</hi> but were <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Feeders</hi> of the Flock; and ſeverall of them were ſet in this one Congregation at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> not as Strangers, meeting there for a ſeaſon, but ſet in it by the Holy Ghoſt, to feed them, and have a care over them, to keep them walking in the ſimplicity of the Truth, and pure Life of Righteouſneſſe, and hence from their Vigilancy over them were they called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Watchers over,</hi> or <hi>Overſeers.</hi> And this is that which is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64127:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>called <hi>Biſhop,</hi> in our Engliſh Tranſlation of Scripture.</p>
               <p>Or if we look upon the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Biſhop,</hi> as taking its riſe from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which are ſoon put together; then (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſignifying, in, among, over, before; and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in Latine, <hi>Meta ad quam Sagittarii collimant,</hi> A Mark to have in ones eye to aim at) then I ſay, the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Biſhop,</hi> imports as much as <hi>A Mark, or example ſet before one to have in ones eye;</hi> one eminent, and worthy to be followed. But I ſtick not upon curious Derivation of Words; whenceſoever the Word is derived, yet the thing underſtood by that Word, contains that in it. And thus CHRIST, <hi>the alone Arch-Biſhop</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>The word</hi> Arch-Biſhop <hi>ſtgnifies</hi> Chief-Biſhop, <hi>and its all one with</hi> Chief-Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard: <hi>and is proper to</hi> Chriſt <hi>alone. Therefore the Apoſtles gave it only to him, calling him</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>that is,</hi> Chief-ſhepheard, 1 Pet. 5.4. <hi>And Chriſt Jeſus ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely forbade this prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence to all his Diſciples, it being proper only to himſelf. So that he that uſurps the Title of</hi> Arch-Biſhop, <hi>or</hi> Chief-Biſhop, <hi>to himſelf, is a</hi> Robber of Chriſts honour; <hi>and ſtands in direct</hi> Rebellion <hi>againſt him in that thing, who ſaid,</hi> It ſhall not be ſo among you, But whoſoever will be chief among you, let him be your Servant, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.16, 17.</note> was a <hi>Mark,</hi> or <hi>Example</hi> to aim at, above all Examples, <hi>Learn of me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for I am meek and lowly in heart:</hi> And next unto him the Holy Apoſtles propounded their own innocent, unblamable Converſation, as an Example or Mark to look at, and follow: <hi>Follow</hi> us (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>for our Converſation is in Heaven,</hi> Phil. 3.17, 20. And they required this ſtill, of all others, who were received as <hi>Biſhops</hi> among the Saints, that they ſhould be men without blame. <hi>A Biſhop</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>muſt be blameleſſe,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.2. That ſo they might be as living Examples, before the reſt. <hi>Not Lords over Gods Heritage, but being Examples to the Flock,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.3. And ſo <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Timothy,</hi> be an <hi>Example to the Flock,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.12. And thus they were <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Leaders,</hi> or <hi>Captains,</hi> by example, and by going before the reſt in a Holy Life, not by a Lordly Power, (for that was excluded plainly, and forbidden both by Chriſt, and by his Apoſtles,) but I ſay, by Example: And therefore they were to be unblameable men, or elſe they were not to be received as <hi>Biſhops,</hi> becauſe they could not be Enſamples to the Flock; if their Life was blamable. Now ſuch as theſe, who walked before the Flock, in a Holy
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64127:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Life; feeding them with the Word of Truth, and leading them in the ſame Steps, by their Example, theſe were called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Ductores, Leaders,</hi> which is tranſlated <hi>Rulers,</hi> Heb. 13.7.17. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Remember them that have he Rule over you,</hi> and Verſ. 17. <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you,</hi> (which Expreſſions they that are out of the feeling of the Life of Truth, are ready to apply to the upholding of an Antichriſtian Power.) But take but the words together, and compare ſpiritual things with ſpiritual, and you will ſee who they were the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, when he names thoſe that have the <hi>rule</hi> over the flock. They were ſuch <hi>Leaders</hi> of the Flock, by their unblameable Example, and pure Faith. Minde his Words, <hi>Ver.</hi> 7. <hi>Remember</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>your Leaders,</hi> (for ſo the VVords are rendred nearer to the Greek) <hi>who have ſpoken to you the Word of God, whoſe faith follow, conſidering the end of their converſation</hi> (what's that?) <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever.</hi> And Verſ. 17. he bids, <hi>Obey ſuch Leaders, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your Souls</hi> (they break their ſleep and eaſe for your Souls,) <hi>as they that muſt give account, that they may do it with joy, and not with grief, for that is unprofitable for you.</hi> See, they were ſuch men whom the Apoſtle bids remember, and follow, and ſubmit to, as were of an exemplary Faith, and of an exemplary Converſation, which had Chriſt, the Meek Lambe of God, for the end of it. Now ſuch <hi>Leaders</hi> as theſe the Lambs are ready to follow, and to ſubmit to, and obey them that thus go before them, leading them by an unblamable Converſation, and by the wholeſome word of Truth. But a Stranger they cannot follow, they cannot follow a Proud Man, a Scornfull Man, an Earthly-minded Man, a Deceitfull Man; a Lording Spirit, that ſeeks an Earthly Kingdome, and Dominion, and to have preheminence here. Such they cannot follow; <hi>As they are Babes and Little Children themſelves,</hi> ſo a <hi>Little Childe muſt lead them.</hi> And ſo the Scripture of the Prophets is fulfilled which Propheſying of the Kingdom of Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>A Little Childe ſhall lead them,</hi> Iſa. 11.6. One thats Innocent, Humble, Meek, Lowly in heart like Chriſt. Pure, Faithfull, Unblamable in his converſation: Such a One ſhall lead, and ſuch a One muſt he be that's a Leader in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64127:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Kingdome of Chriſt. Not a Great pufft up proud Lord. For he by his Example leads quite from the Kingdom of God, whither the Lambs are going, and leads into the Pomp and Vanities of this preſent world, from which they are flying, and againſt which he made others to promiſe and vow; though he be the forwardeſt to lead into them. How ſhould the Lambs follow ſuch a one? judge you, and judge as you will be judged.</p>
               <p>Again further, The Faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>(which is the evidence of things not ſeen, and the ſubſtance, or being, of things hoped for)</hi> This Faith, I ſay, is not conſiſtent with Exaltation, and Greatneſſe, and Lordſhip among the Miniſters of Chriſt. Therefore ſaith Chriſt Jeſus to ſuch, <hi>How can ye believe, who receive honour one of another, and ſeek not the honour that cometh of God only?</hi> John 5.44. You may ſee, he looks upon ſuch, as out of the Faith. For obſerve, the ground of it lies thus. His Faith, or the Faith that he works, which is the Faith of his Kingdome is not a dead blind thing, ſuch as the Faith of the world is: But it is a clear ſight, Evidence, or Demonſtration of things not ſeen; even of the things of his Kingdome, which the carnall eye ſees not, nor the bodily eye; Now, where doth a man come to this Sight or evidence, this open view, (as I may ſay) of things ſpiritual, wherein the Faith of Chriſts Kingdome conſiſts? Chriſt himſelf hath told us, It is in a Low Place, that is, in a Low Condition, the ſtate of a Little Childe, as of one new born; And except a man come to this, <hi>He cannot ſee the Kingdome of God.</hi> For while the minde and heart of the Creature is pregnant, or filled with deſires, and affections that are of this world, there is no room for things ſpiritual, and eternal to enter: Neither doth he obtain the ſight of them from the Lord, for, <hi>It's to Babes that he reveals them.</hi> Therefore a man muſt be emptyed, and brought down as a Childe, before God open to him the Treaſures of his Kingdome. God <hi>hides</hi> the things of his Kingdome, and keeps them back from the High and Lofty, who are big with Wiſdome, and Prudence, and Learning; and <hi>reveales them unto Babes,</hi> (praiſed be his Name therefore) <hi>He repleniſhes the Humble and Hungry with Good Things, but the Rich he ſends Empty away. The Proud he beholds a farr off.</hi> his Eye is upon ſuch a one to bring him low, and abaſe him. So
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64127:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>that as men grow great and high, and lift up themſelves, they go out from the place or condition of ſeeing the things of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God: they go from the condition to which God ſhews them, and to which he gives the evidence and demonſtration of them inwardly by his Spirit: and ſo this is to go out from the Faith of Chriſt, which conſiſts in this evidence, or ſight, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration ſhining into the ſoul, and giving poſſeſſion of the thing ſeen unto the ſoul. <hi>And therefore how can ye believe, who receive Honour one of another,</hi> and go up into Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, out of the ſight of the Kingdom which is Spiritual? The lower that the Creature becomes, the more capable he is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of the Spiritual Treaſure, and the further he enters into the Kingdom that is Spiritual, and not of this World; but the higher he grows in this Worlds Pomp, and Greatneſs, and Glory, the further off he goes from the Faith of Chriſt: So that one may ſay to ſuch, <hi>How can ye believe?</hi> And here we ſtand upon firm ground, in denying the <hi>POPE,</hi> who takes the title of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop;</hi> and in denying all other <hi>Lording Biſhops,</hi> followers of his ſteps; I ſay, we ſtand upon firm ground in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying them all, as men gone far, far, far off from the Paths of ſuch <hi>Biſhops</hi> as the Scriptures own; and are fallen under the temptation which Satan preſented before Chriſt, even <hi>the glory of this World:</hi> And whither then can they lead us by their Example? Conſider it well. The <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> conſiſts of <hi>little Children,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, and <hi>a little Child muſt lead them;</hi> and not ſuch as are great, and ſeek preheminence: ſuch are gone out from the Faith, and follow the ſteps of <hi>Diotrephes, who loved to have the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence</hi> (that thing which Chriſt had forbidden) 3 Epiſt. <hi>Joh.</hi> ver. 9, 10. ſhews you what he did. He began to be a <hi>Wolf</hi> in the Church of Chriſt, when he had entred into the love of <hi>Preheminence.</hi> And ſo it muſt be with thoſe that follow his ſteps; It cannot be otherwiſe, eſpecially now ſince the Myſtery of Iniquity hath formed and founded a <hi>Politick Kingdom</hi> for their great ſpirits to riſe in, in the ſimilitude of the World (though under the pretence of Chriſts Church) And ſo they cannot be Examples to the Flock, if they would, but muſt be <hi>Devourers</hi> thereof; The very Myſtery that they have given up themſelves into, will force them to be <hi>Devourers</hi> and <hi>Scatterers</hi> of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64127:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Flock; though ſome of them may have a pitty ariſing ſometimes in their hearts, and would not; yet the Myſtery of Iniquity is ſo deeply founded, that it carries them on who come into it whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will or no, to help to bear it up againſt the Lambs of Chriſt: As a Wheel in a Clock is forced on by the motion of other Wheels: So it is in this great Myſtery. And ſo the Lambs cannot look upon any that manage a place in the Kingdom of that Myſtery, as full Friends and Examples, but as Enemies and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers, and Scatterers. And ſo it hath been, ever ſince this Myſtery of Iniquity got up, The Lambs have been ſcattered and devoured, and trampled upon by that ſpirit that loves the Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence. And hereof there hath been ſufficient proof: For though thoſe Wolves have gloried in the Church, the Church, (as the Maſters of Aſſemblies and Provinces) yet the Church hath been trod in the dirt by them. And therefore if any one would look back upon the Church of Chriſt, and view the ſtate of it for many hundreds of years paſt; they muſt not look upon the National Epiſcopal Churches, to think to ſee it there; but upon them who have been devoured, ſcattered, perſecuted, ſlain, kept under, and trod upon by thoſe Epiſcopal and National Churches. If you would ſee the true Church where it hath been in theſe times paſt, <hi>See it there under Perſecution by the Biſhops,</hi> and by others that loved to have the Preheminence; or elſe you cannot ſee it at all: For the <hi>Biſhops Churches,</hi> and ſuch as theirs, have been but the <hi>Outward Court, given to the Gentiles,</hi> which have troden the holy City under foot, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.2. And ſo the Dominion and Greatneſs, and Lordſhip, ſuch as the Lords of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles uſe, (which was forbidden by Chriſt among his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.25, 26.) This they could bring into the <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Court,</hi> which is given to the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> becauſe it's anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and their nature. And ſo the Outward Court hath had the manner of the Gentiles Government in it, and it hath been ſutable to them: But whoſoever comes to be a little Child in the Kingdom of Chriſt Jeſus, he will find it unſutable to his ſpirit; and that he muſt lye down as a Sufferer under it, as his fellow-ſervants have done, who have ſuffered great Tribulation under it, and have been trampled under foot by it for hundreds of years, And here hath been the ſtate of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64127:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Church of Chriſt, the holy City, It hath been ſore ſhot at, by Words, Revilings, Reproaches, Blaſphemies, ſeveral Nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names, Perſecutions, Tribulations, which it hath endured under the great prevailing Myſtery of Iniquity, which hath prevailed over Multitudes, Nations, Kings, Tongues, Peoples: But yet <hi>(though it hath had the ſtrength of the Gates of Hell)</hi> it could not prevail againſt this <hi>Little Flock of the Lambs of Christ,</hi> (according as Chriſt promiſed to <hi>Peter</hi>) who have ſtill riſen <hi>(though troden under foot)</hi> and have been made to witneſſe againſt it, in ſome part of it or other. Nor ſhall it ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt the Lambs, the true Church, to root them out, as it deſires. The time is near for the tumbling down of thoſe Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries again; and then <hi>Wo, Wo,</hi> and <hi>Wailing</hi> will be the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them that are found therein.</p>
               <p>And ſo now you may ſee <hi>whither they are gone that ſeek Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence,</hi> and <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> and <hi>Lordſhip in the Kingdom of Chriſt:</hi> They are gone out from the Doctrine of Chriſt; they are gone out from the Faith of Chriſt, and ſo from the Fellowſhip of God, 2 <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. <hi>For God dwels not with the high and lofty, but with the lowly in heart, with him that is of an humble and contrite heart;</hi> ſuch as the Doctrine of Chriſt teacheth us to be. From all theſe things they are gone out, who exalt themſelves as Lords over Gods Heritage. <hi>Whither then are they gone?</hi> Even into the World, and ſo into the Enmity with God: for, <hi>he that will be the Friend of the World</hi> (by loving the things of it) <hi>he makes himſelf the Enemy of God:</hi> And ſo they ſtand in the Enmity, not in Amity with God; in the World, not in the Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For it's in the World where the gods many, and lords many are. There be, faith <hi>Paul, <hi>gods</hi> many, and <hi>lords</hi> many; but to us</hi> (who are in the Church, and of the Church of Chriſt) <hi>there is but <hi>one God</hi>
                  </hi> the <hi>
                     <hi>Father,</hi> and <hi>one Lord</hi>
                  </hi> (namely) <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.5. Now, if to us there be but <hi>one Lord,</hi> who is <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> as the Apoſtle affirms: Then where is there any place among us for the <hi>many Lords?</hi> If any other will be <hi>Lord,</hi> muſt be not go out into the World to receive his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> there? ſeeing there can be no more Lords admitted of among us <hi>
                     <hi>but</hi> One,</hi> who is the <hi>Lord JESUS CHRIST.</hi> And therefore that was a common phraſe of ſpeech among the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64127:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Diſciples of Chriſt, to ſay, <hi>Our Lord JESUS CHRIST</hi> or, <hi>CHRIST JESUS <hi>our Lord,</hi>
                  </hi> acknowledging and aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing that peculiar Prerogative over them, to him alone. And therefore the Apoſtles did forbid others to be <hi>Lords,</hi> or, <hi>as Lords over Gods Heritage;</hi> and bid them be <hi>Enſamples to the Flock,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Impreſſions</hi> (as it were) or <hi>Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps</hi> for them to walk in. Now, how can they be <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples,</hi> and leave <hi>Impreſſions</hi> for the Lambs of <hi>CHRIST'S Kingdome</hi> to walk in, of Meekneſſe and Lowly-mindedneſs, who get up into Greameſs and High-mindedneſs? who love the World, and ſeek to be great in it? Can theſe be <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> to the Flock of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> teaching them by their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to walk humbly with God, and lowly in heart, not loving this preſent evil world, nor the Pomp and Glory of it, who get into the Pomp and Glory, and Greatneſſe of it themſelves? If this be to be Enſamples, to go a quite contrary way; then may we as well ſay, That a Coward that runs from his Colours, is an example of Courage; or that a Drunkard or Glutton is an example of Temperance; or that thoſe who turned back in their hearts to <hi>Egypt,</hi> were examples of perſeverance in the journey to <hi>Canaan,</hi> whom God ſlew in the Wilderneſſe, that they never ſaw the borders of <hi>Canaan.</hi> And it were well if all the back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliders in heart, who for the Love of this preſent evil World do turn their backs of the Spiritual Kingdom of God, would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this, and call to mind the hand of the Lord againſt them, and fear before him; for his hand is not ſhortned. And confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeriouſly with your ſelves in coolneſſe of ſpirit, If you think in your conſetences, that the righteous and holy God will be thus mocked by them that ſhall pretend to be his Servants; namely, to have them to thruſt themſelves into thoſe places, and under thoſe names where they ſhould be examples of humility, to teach his little Flock by their examples, to be humble and lowly in heart, and then to lead them a quite contrary way by their example: Yea, to enjoyn others by words, (before they admit them into the Congregation of Chriſts Flock, as they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it in their <hi>Common-Prayer-Book;</hi> I ſay, before they admit them to enjoyn them) <hi>to promiſe and vow, <hi>to forſake the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and all his Works,</hi>
                  </hi> (and in particular) <hi>the vain pomp and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64127:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>glory of the World, and all the covetous deſires of the ſame;</hi> and then by their example teach them the contrary, and ſet a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern before them of embracing this preſent evil World (like <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi>) and of getting up into the vain pomp and glory of it.</p>
               <p>Judge righteouſly in the fear of God, and let the Light of <hi>Chriſt</hi> have place in your hearts; and judge righteouſly for God, if ſuch be not Enemies to the Croſſe of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and Enemies to your Souls, keeping them in darkneſſe and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by their earthly and carnal converſation, and loving of this preſent Worlds glory: and whether you are ever like to come to ſee the Kingdom of God by following them, who are gone ſo far from the path of it themſelves?</p>
               <p>Trifle not with God, for he will not be mocked. And he is bringing up again into ſight and poſſeſſion that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom (praiſes be to his Name) which hath long been troden under foot in the outward Court, by ſuch as are of this World, and love the greatneſſe and glory of it, (as the Gentles do) and are therefore counted and called by him Gentiles, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.2.</p>
               <p>And now kiſs the Son of Righteouſneſs which is ariſing, leſt he be angry, and ye periſh out of his way (as ſome have done) when his wrath is kindled but a little; And let go the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Vanities, wherewith the Nations have been deceived for a long time; and turn to his pure Truth, and embrace his pure Doctrine according as he left it, and come to live in it, and to find your Teacher near you, that you may find fellowſhip with God in your ſouls. So ſhall you ſoon become wiſer than your Teachers, and wiſer than your Ancients, and grave Doctors and great Lords; and you ſhall witneſſe the words of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt true in your ſelves, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. ver. 99, 100.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64127:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Touching the <hi>Common-prayer-Book.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen Chriſt aſcended up on high, <hi>he gave Gifts to men for the Work of his Miniſtry;</hi> and ſo they were every one <hi>to adminiſter as of the Ability which God gave: That God in all things might be glorified, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.11. which Gifts the Spirit of God did enable them with, <hi>diſtributing to every one ſeverally as he pleaſed:</hi> And they were to do the Work of their Miniſtry as from that Ability, that God might be glorified for his mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Gifts. And ſo the Apoſtles they kept to that: If they preached, they <hi>ſpake as the Spirit gave them utterance,</hi> and ſo bad others do ſo, to ſpeak <hi>as God gave ability;</hi> and, <hi>as the Oracles of God.</hi> If they prayed, they prayed as the Spirit en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled them. <hi>We know not what to pray for as we ought,</hi> ſayes <hi>Paul, but the Spirit helpeth our infirmities.</hi> It was not a <hi>Book</hi> that helped their infirmities in Preaching, or Praying; but it was the <hi>Spirit.</hi> So here was their ability, in <hi>the Spirit,</hi> not in <hi>a Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then afterwards, as men degenerated from the Truth, and went out from the Doctrine of Chriſt, and of the Apoſtles, and ſought to be great, and have preheminence in the Earth; here they went out from Communion with God, and his holy Spirit; and ſo the Spirit of the Lord withdrawing, and leaving them, they were left deſtitute of that help. And then wanting the aſſiſtance and ſupply of the Spirit of God, they went to work another way, to uphold their Miniſtry; and invented Forms of Prayer to be a help, which they could at all times make uſe of, though the Spirit of God had withdrawn it ſelf. And this ſupply now would ſerve any one to help them in that Miniſtry, which was ſutable enough to their earthly Kingdom. And ſo here grew up all manner of Superſtitions and Inventions, now when the Spirit had withdrawn it ſelf; and the bottomleſs Pit was opened, and ſmoke came up out of the Pit, which darkened all: and here grew up the Myſtery of Iniquity to an Head, to a City, to a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64127:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>compacted Form and Method, and Government, like the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; and now makes war with the Saints, and with them that ſtood in the ſimplicity of the Spirit, and would not become one with them in this their humane, invented, eſtranged way, in which they were gone aſtray. And ſo this City grew to be a great City, ſpreading over Multitudes, Tongues, Kings, Peoples, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: And it trod under foot <hi>the little City of God,</hi> that <hi>Holy City,</hi> his <hi>Little Flock,</hi> which could not joyn with them in their invenced wayes. And this great City prevailed much over the Saints and Servants of God; and boaſted much, and gloried over all, ſaying in her heart, <hi>I ſit as Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EEN:</hi> and ſo compelled all great and ſmall to take this her <hi>Cup of Fornication,</hi> and drink thereof: and ſhe hath prevailed to make them drunk therewith, And whoſoever would not come and drink of her Cup, nothing was to be expected by them, but Tribulation from her. And ſo they have found it ſufficiently, and felt it from her hands. As the Scripture alſo witneſſeth, in ſeveral places of the Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> which was given forth to declare of that <hi>Whores Reign,</hi> before it came. Now this <hi>degenerated Epiſcopacy,</hi> or <hi>Biſhops way,</hi> which is gone out from the Doctrine of Chriſt, and from his holy Spirit, and ſtands in an Earthly Power and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, cannot well tell how to ſubſiſt, and uphold its Kingdom and Miniſtry, without ſome ſuch ſupply as a <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> which may be ready for them, and help them, though the Spirit have left them. Yet that it might be taking in the minds of people, they have compoſed it of as many good words as they can: which Satan can well give way to, ſo long as it ſtands in the Diſobedience and Oppoſition to the Kingdom of Chriſt, and of his Spirit. And ſo it is a golden Cup which this Whore hath in her hand, as well in that reſpect, (having many good words, and fair expreſſions in it, to deceive the minds of the ſimple) as alſo in regard of the Outward Treaſure, that it is made the way to; there being no liberty to any to trade and grow rich with the Merchandize of that Kingdom, but ſuch as ſhall conform thereto; and ſuch have a <hi>bait of Gold,</hi> and outward glory, and preferment attainable fet before their eyes, in the examples of others, <hi>as a Mark</hi> for them to aim at. And ſo <hi>herein</hi> their <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> and <hi>Maſters</hi> of that Worſhip are Examples to their Flock.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64127:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>And ſo here's a ſutableneſs between theſe three, namely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>The exalted Spirit</hi> (that's gone out from Chriſt, and from his Doctrine, after the World) and between <hi>her Cup,</hi> and <hi>the Fornicators with her;</hi> all of the World, all out from the Spirit; and ſo being of one nature, all three acquieſce in one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and joyn hand in hand to uphold one another. But where is the Babe, that's truly regenerated from above, and born again by the Spirit of God, that can now joyn in the upholding of ſuch a dead ſpiritleſs Sacrifice, ſince the Light of Chriſt hath ſo ſhined forth to make it manifeſt from whence it is? Have not the Lambs of Chriſt formerly been perſecuted and ſlain, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing Conformity with the Whore in her Worſhip, ſo far as they ſaw Light againſt it? and can they do any leſſe now? For they find it not ſuitable to that Spirit which they are born again of.</p>
               <p>Judge in your ſelves by the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Witneſſe of God; Is it ſuitable to the <hi>New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, a Covenant inwardly written in the heart</hi> by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the living God, in which a Creature is to be led of the Spirit, and guided by the Spirit, and in which he ſtands in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, having acceſſe to God in that Spirit that gives him the feeling of his preſence, and teaches him what to pray, forming in his heart ſtrong deſires and earnings after God and his Righteouſneſſe, and forming in him a filial frame of Spirit, in which he cryes <hi>Abba, Father:</hi> and in which he can draw near unto God as a Father. Is it ſuitable to ſuch a <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> as this, wherein God doth thus ſet at liberty inwardly his <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Daughters,</hi> and enlarge their priviledges in the Spirit, and give them ſuch acceſs to him to worſhip him in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? Judge in your ſelves, is it ſuitable to this Covenant, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex to it a dead literal formal <hi>Common-Prayer-Book?</hi> the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of which may be performed without any meaſure of the Spirit of the New Covenant; yea, by ſuch as are ſo far off from that Spirit in which the New Covenant and its Miniſtry ſtands, that they make a mock thereat? But the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> ſtanding in Oppoſition to that Spirit, which they mock at and deſpiſe, and ſtand in oppoſition to themſelves, hence both ſtanding in one ground, They love it, and hug it; for being in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64127:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>the ſame ground, that unites. Hence it is that the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> gets ſo much affection and approbation from all ſorts of debauched and wicked livers: they can generally flock to that as to their own; for it ſprung from that root in which they ſtand; both out of the New Covenant; both ſtrangers to the Spirit of God. They being dead to the Life of the Spirit, and not knowing what it is to be led thereby; and it alſo being dead as to the miniſtring of the Spirit, a dead thing which any dead man may perform, and be accepted of by them that impoſe it, though he be a Hater of the wayes of the Spirit of God. A Drunkard, Swearer, Lyar, any Prophane Perſon that hath not taſted of the Gifts of the Spirit of God, given for Edification of the Body. Yea, Scoffers, Scorners, Deriders at the Spirit, ſuch as are ſo far off from the New Covenant of the Spirit, that they taunt and kick at the very owning of the Spirit, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme them that own it <hi>(as may be proved by ſeveral Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies)</hi> Yet ſuch can perform that Miniſtry of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> becauſe it's a dead thing, ſuitable to their dead hearts; and which they can do in their dead condition, and well admit of, without diſturbing of themſelves in their dead condition: and can pleaſe their dead conſciences therewith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it lets them be at reſt in the death of ſin, where they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to be, unwakened, under death. And ſo Death is miniſtred unto by Death; and Death delights in Death; and the Dead are kept in their Graves by that which is dead: As common experience hath daily given teſtimony. For where are they that are awakened out of the death of Sin, into the life of the Spirit by that dead thing? But it's even as a long over one aſleep, to keep them in that ſleep.</p>
               <p>It pitties my heart to ſee what deep Aegyptian Darkneſſe is upon the Hearts of many, who thruſt themſelves into the Miniſtry, <hi>(as pretending for CHRIST,)</hi> And yet are ſo ignorant of the things that pertain to the Kingdome of God, as that they underſtand not by what ability that Miniſtry is to be upheld. But ſet upon it, as in purſuit of an earthly Kingdome to themſelves, <hi>(as indeed theirs is)</hi> and that with ſuch carnal ſupplies and furniture, wherewith they have furniſhed themſelves; as any meer carnal Man may have, who hath no ſavour of things
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64127:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpiritual: Thou blind man that dareſt uphold ſuch a dead Service and Worſhip: Doſt thou not know, that <hi>CHRIST JESUS aſcended up on high, and gave Gifts to men for the work of his Miniſtry under the New COVENANT?</hi> And were not all they that did Miniſter, to miniſter <hi>as of that ability</hi> which God gave, in, and by the Spirit, as a fruit of CHRISTS Aſcention? And ſo were <hi>not now to be Ministers of a dead Letter, but of the Spirit,</hi> by miniſtring to others in the Spirit, as the Spirit miniſtred to them. And ſo as the Covenant is ſpirituall, ſo is the Miniſtry ſpirituall. As the Covenant <hi>is not a Covenant written in Tables of Stone,</hi> or Braſs, or Paper, or Wood, <hi>but in the heart by the ſpirit;</hi> ſo the Miniſtry muſt anſwer it. It muſt be alſo a Miniſtry, not ſtanding in Books and Writings, outwardly read; but in Gifts of the ſame Spirit. And this the Apoſtles held out clearly in their Practice and Doctrine. And let the Wiſdome of Men reaſon what it will to the contrary; and plead according to its carnal Underſtanding: Yet ſeeing Chriſt our Lord, and the Mediatour of the New Covenant, and Eſtabliſher of the Miniſtry thereof, hath appointed that it ſhould be ſo, (namely, that his Miniſtry ſhould be performed by the Abilities of the Spirit, which he aſcended to give,) We ought therein to reſt, and not to ſtrive againſt his Will and Wiſdome; nor to impoſe Inventions of men into any part of his Miniſtry: <hi>(So ſetting our will againſt his, and our Wiſdome against his:)</hi> For ſo to do is <hi>Whoredome</hi> of Spirit from Chriſt; its <hi>Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, Idolatry, Stubbornneſſe, Rebellion,</hi> and the <hi>Prop of Antichriſt,</hi> a <hi>Cup of Fornication,</hi> ſuch as the Nations are made drunk with, and upon which the wrath of God will come, becauſe of Rebellion therein againſt his Son. Even as his wrath came upon Iſrael after the fleſh, for their wilfulneſſe in following their own Wiſdome, and Traditions of other Nations, and would not be guided by his Directions then under the Firſt Covenant: And their Examples are written for our Admonition.</p>
               <p>If any ſay to me, That <hi>Good men,</hi> and ſome <hi>Martyrs</hi> have ſuffered for the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> I Anſwer, I deny not but <hi>Good Men,</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> have ſuffered thus far on the behalf of it: that is, They have teſtifyed againſt Service in another tongue which they underſtood not, and ſo born teſtimony for the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:64127:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>againſt the <hi>Maſſe-Book,</hi> which was in Latine; that is as much as to ſay, They have teſtified for the having it in a known Tongue, againſt the having it in an unknown Tongue. And ſo here was one ſtep forward from the diſmall darkneſſe of Egypt ſpirituall. And their faithfulneſſe in that was accepted of God; and the reſt winked at. But now that the true Light makes more ſtill manifeſt, we are to teſtifie againſt that which is further opened to be evil in it; and to be faithfull to that, as they were to what they ſaw.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Tender <hi>ADMONITION</hi> to all thoſe called PRIESTS, or MINISTERS.</head>
               <p>O Ye that are called <hi>Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who preach to the people for hire, and keep them in a Forme without the Power, Is it poſſible, that a <hi>Word of experience, <hi>(ſhewed me in the ſpirit, being kept low with the Lord, and in his fear)</hi>
                  </hi> may reach any of you, I could willingly tell it you, for my heart pitties you, as you are men, and I ſhould rejoyce in your Salvation, as well as of others. But I ſee you ſtand in greateſt danger of all men, both by reaſon you have ſtrengthened your ſelves in your holds by ſeeming Arguments, and Interpretations of Scripture, and Opinions of Men: And alſo becauſe Truth ſtrikes directly at your <hi>Diana,</hi> by which you ſubſiſt, and have your livelihood <hi>(as you call it)</hi> Therefore its hard for you to lend an ear to hear <hi>the Voice</hi> that calls out: or to open your eye to let in a glimpſe of that light that diſcovers it. For if ſuch a thought or motion do but offer it ſelf, I know Satan followes it immediately with this at the heels: <hi>What then will become of us?</hi> Oh that there were faith in you, to truſt God for your outward being and ſupply! and a contented heart to live at Gods allowance. Then would the Teachings of Truth more eaſily enter, and finde place. And verily truſt him, and let your eye be open to ſee the light which would ſhine into your own Conſciences, if your unbelief did not ſtop it, and if your loving this preſent evil world, and the deeds of darkneſſe, did not keep
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64127:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>you back from coming to it. For he that loves truth, comes to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt that they are wrought in God. Truſt God I ſay for your outward ſubſiſtence, (and he will not forſake you utterly) and let the light ariſe in your conſciences, concerning your wayes: and <hi>ſeek first the Kingdom of God, and the Righteouſneſſe thereof,</hi> and you have the words of Chriſt for it, which is above the word of any King (who is Truth it ſelf and cannot lye) <hi>that all theſe things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> I have found his word true by experience, everlaſting praiſes to his name. And Oh how could I rejoyce to ſee your hearts brought down out of your formall wayes, into the Obedience and power of Truth! That you might not ſtand as a ſtop in the ſtrait way, hindring your own and others return unto God in the way of his Covenant. My heart envies you not, (I ſpeak in the preſence of the Lord,) but in a tender Compaſſion to you I ſpeak thus plainly and familiarly to you: longing even for your Salvation alſo; that if it be poſſible you might be delivered out of that deep pit in which you are faln. For I have ſeen your horrid darkneſſe in which you ſtand. God in mercy ſhewed it unto me, and kept me out of it. And I ſaw plainly, that if I had entred into your livings (as they are called) I had entred into it. But bleſſed be his name that kept me, and allured me into the wilderneſſe, there to feel his love, and made me to ſit down weeping in remembrance of ZION, which I ſaw to be farr off, and troden under foot by the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which had got into the <hi>outward Court;</hi> and were there glorying in their Ordinances: and crying out upon others as <hi>Seducers</hi> and <hi>Deluders,</hi> and <hi>Hereticks,</hi> while the HOLY CITY was troden under foot among themſelves. But the Lord hath ſhewed me upon whom the ſtrong deluſions are ſent: and for what Cauſe. It is upon the diſobedient, who have pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe: and for that cauſe, becauſe they love that, and chuſe unrighteouſneſſe to live in, rather than the fear of God. Therefore doth the Lord ſend them ſtrong deluſions, even to believe a lye. Come down to become as little Children, and you will ſee the ſame alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And I tell you plainly, untill you do come down, to become as little Children, you cannot ſee God, you cannot ſee the Kingdome of God; you cannot judge righteouſly,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64127:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the things of the Kingdome of God. For how ſhould you judge right of things that you cannot ſee?</p>
               <p>Therefore humble your ſelves under the mighty hand of God; and fear him, who will make all bow before him, and ſtoop to his will, one way or other. And ſtand not upon your Learning, or Parts, or any ſuch thing: For ſuch things are of light account in the ſight of God: but come down to the place where God feeds his Babes: even a low place it is: a place of poverty of Spirit, a place of mourning, a place of hungring and thirſting. And I tell you till you come thither, you ſhall never feel any thing of the preſence of God to your everlaſting comfort. And if you miſſe this, what good will your Learning with all your vaunting do you? Will it not all vaniſh away with vexation, when an evill conſcience ariſes, and torment there enters, and abides tormenting you in the preſence of God, and his holy Angels, becauſe you have neglected the one thing needfull: even to walk with him in his fear, in his pure light; and ſo in a good conſcience kept clear in the ſight of God? For without this the blood of Chriſt cleanſeth you not from your ſins. Mind that, leſt you daub up your ſelves with untempered mortar. I ſay, the Blood of Chriſt cleanſeth you not in the way of an evil Conſcience, in walking contrary to the Light of Chriſt. But ſaith <hi>John, If we walk in the Light, as God is in the Light, then have we fellowſhip — and the blood cleanſes.</hi> But walking contrary to the Light, there is made ſhipwrack of a good Conſcience, and the Conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns, and God is greater than the Conſcience, to condemn.</p>
               <p>Conſider it deeply; for it is writ in Love and Faithfulneſſe to your ſouls, by one that yearns after your good, and not after your deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:64127:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN EXHORTATION to Thoſe that have ſeperated Themſelves from the SUPERSTITIONS of the PRIESTS.</head>
            <p>YOU that have turned your backs of AEGYPT <hi>(ſpiritually ſo called)</hi> and have ſuffered hard Speeches, and Reproaches, and Injuries of Wicked Men, in coming out of their groſſer Abominations and Superſtitions; There is a tender reſpect in my heart towards you, who have done this, in obedience to a Principle of God in your hearts: And my Deſire for you is, That You may not loſe your Reward, by looking back again to AEGYPT: or by turning aſide to this preſent evill World: or to any of the hurtfull Luſts therein: or by taking up your Habitation ſhort of the <hi>Land of Reſt:</hi> But that you may be preſerved in that tender Principle that led you forth, that therein you may go forward and not backward. But now do not think that you are come to the end of your journey, becauſe You have ſtepped out of Egypt. Remember the <hi>many Journeys and Removes</hi> the Iſraelites had after
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64127:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>they came out of Egypt, before they arrived at the good Land of Promiſe; and faint not, but gird up the loyns of your mindes. Only take heed of thoſe things that cauſed many to fall in the way, and be not diſcouraged though <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſeem to purſue you with an Hoſte: For the <hi>Egyptians</hi> may be hardened to purſue to their own deſtruction, and to proſecute the Seed as if they would ſwallow them up: Look to him that led you out, and hold on your way: follow the Pillar of ſmoke and of fire, <hi>the Power and preſence of God,</hi> that his wing may be over you: and take heed of murmuring at the difficulty of the way, as ſome murmured and periſhed: for <hi>Strait is the gate, and narrow is the way that leadeth unto Life.</hi> Take heed of <hi>unbelief,</hi> for that enters not into the <hi>Promiſe:</hi> It's Faith that overcomes: In that go on and make war with the enemies of your ſouls, that are in the way, ſpare none, ſuffer no ſecret luſt to remain alive in your hearts: but let the ſword of the Spirit come over them, to mortifie and ſlay them; and do not ſatisfie your ſelves becauſe you have got into this or that <hi>Forme:</hi> for, What will that avail you, if you go no further? It's the <hi>life and power</hi> that the Kingdom of God conſiſts in: See that you ſit not down ſhort of that. Are you come to <hi>Truth and Faithfulneſſe</hi> in your hearts, ſo that the world finding your honeſt; plain, faithfull Converſation, dare truſt you, and commit any thing they have to you in aſſurance that they ſhall not be defrauded or deceived by you? If you be not, but live in Covetouſneſſe and Deceit, its neither your departing from Egypt, nor ſitting down under any Form whatſoever that will do you any good. For you are
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64127:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>not yet come to the Kingdome of God, which is in Righteouſneſſe and Truth. Are you come to an <hi>unblamable converſation</hi> before men, ſo that they have nothing juſtly to charge you with, and to a <hi>good conſcience</hi> before God, which anſwers to the Light of the Lord in you, and ſo accuſes not? Are you come to <hi>Mercy,</hi> and to a tender compaſſionate heart that delights in it; and ſeeks to ſave your fellow-creature, and not to deſtroy the life of any, but only to deliver it from that which would deſtroy? If not, the nature of the Saviour is not yet formed in you. Are you come to the <hi>Light</hi> which lets you ſee your hearts, and all the ſecret thoughts and intents, and purpoſes of them; and to love it, and turn to it, and follow it? Are you come to the <hi>New-Covenant,</hi> to receive the Law of God in the Spirit, from Chriſt the Mediator thereof, who is the Lord, that Spirit that miniſters it: and ſo to hear the word thats nigh you in the mouth, and in the heart? Are you come to feel the <hi>Anointing</hi> abiding in you, which keeps you abiding in Chriſt, as you are taught thereby: and which diſcovers to you Seducings and Deluſions of that ſpirit of Antichriſt, that works to lead you from it? Are you come to that <hi>inward fellowſhip and communion with God,</hi> which the Apoſtles of the Lamb enjoyed, and ſought to bring the babes of Chriſt unto? Are you come to feel the <hi>vvorking of that Spirit</hi> of truth in you, <hi>vvhich mortifies</hi> the deeds of the fleſh, which would hinder your communion with God? Are you come to that ſpirit <hi>that renewes and ſanctifies,</hi> and <hi>changes</hi> your hearts, and <hi>caſts out</hi> the old man with his deeds; and brings forth <hi>love</hi> inſtead of hatred, <hi>patience</hi> inſtead of frowardneſſe and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64127:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>haſtineſſe, <hi>lovvlineſſe</hi> of minde inſtead of loftineſſe, <hi>harmleſneſſe</hi> inſtead of hurting, <hi>pitty</hi> inſtead of hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartedneſſe, <hi>gentleneſſe</hi> inſtead of roughneſſe, <hi>faith</hi> inſtead of fear and diſtruſt, <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> inſtead of guile and deceitfulneſſe, <hi>temperance and ſobriety</hi> inſtead of exceſſe, and ſuch like wholſom fruits as theſe inſtead of the contrary? Are you come to that which thus ſtrikes at Iniquity when it would appear in you, and cuts it down; and brings forth the contrary? Are you come, I ſay, <hi>to that ſpirit vvhich is the Root</hi> from whence all good fruits do ſpring; which is that good Land which flowes with milk and hony; that Promiſed Land, that true Reſting-place? If you be not come to theſe things, How can you think your ſelves at a period? How can you think that you are come to Canaan ſpirituall where ſuch fruits as theſe grow? How can you ſit down as if you were already got into the good Land? <hi>Come gird up the loyns of your minde, and go forvvard vvith us.</hi> Let us preſſe on to perfection; having our faces ſtill forward in that Kingdome, the Treaſures of which have no end; And clogg not your ſelves with the love of this preſent evill world, for that will preſſe you down, and keep you back, and be a weight to you. Minde the one thing needfull, and preſſe toward the mark, of the high-Calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Will it ſatisfie you to break off from Egypt, if you periſh in the Wilderneſſe, and fall ſhort of the promiſed Land, the Land of Peace and Reſt; even the <hi>Promiſe of the Father, The Spirit of Truth, the Comforter,</hi> which leads into all truth, and into that righteouſneſs, the work of which is peace, and the effect of which is
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64127:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>quietneſſe, and aſſurance for ever? Iſa. 32.17. Will you make that a Poſſeſſion for ever, where you had but a Lodging place (as it were) for a night or two, while the Pillar of ſmoke and fire ſtood over it? Will you ſtay behinde the cloudy pillar when it is lifted up and gone forward? Will you not go along with the power in which the Kingdom of God ſtands? Doth not the Apoſtle call out of the Form when the Power is gone? Come, Let us go forward together, not looking back again to <hi>Sodom,</hi> as <hi>Lots Wife</hi> did, who was therefore turned into a <hi>Pillar of Salt:</hi> nor as they did who ſaid, Come, let us make a Captain and turn back to Egypt, whoſe carcaſſes therefore fell in the Wilderneſſe. <hi>Remember Caleb and Joſhua</hi> who followed the Lord fully with all their heart, whom the Lord therefore ſet into the Land of <hi>Promiſe;</hi> who preſſed ſtill forward, when others began to hang back through fear of the <hi>lofty Giants;</hi> whoſe Faith follow. And take heed of luſting after evill things, as they luſted who fell by the way. Come down out of all Exaltation from any Form that you are got into, be it what it will; and come into meekneſſe, lowlineſſe of heart, humbleneſſe of mind, gentleneſſe in the fear of the Lord; and become as Little Chidren, for in plainneſſe of Speech, this is the way that our Captain is gone before us, and hath left word for us to follow him in. Take my Yoke upon you, and learn of me, (ſaith he) for I am meek, and lowly in heart; and you ſhall finde reſt for your ſoules: for my yoak is eaſie, and my burthen is light.</p>
            <p>Bear with me in my pleading thus with you. For we would not have you loſt who have borne the abuſes of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64127:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>the world, and the fury of a wicked and untoward Generation for Conſcience ſake. Be not weary, nor faint in your mindes; nor ſay in your hearts, <hi>Where is the Promiſe of his coming?</hi> for one day is with the Lord as a thouſand years, and a thouſand years as one day. In his time he will come and not fail. Happy is he that endures to the end, waiting for him. He ſhall reap that faints not. My Affections are towards you who have ſeen the <hi>great Whores Cup of Fornication,</hi> and have through ſufferings broke off from her with us. If you be low enough for our Company we would not loſe you. Is it not the ſame God that we preſſe after? Is it not the ſame fellowſhip with him inwardly in the ſoul? Is it not the ſame bread that comes down from Heaven, which you would feed upon, to the inward ſatisfaction and content of your ſouls, which is the ſtrength of our hearts, and which we feed upon, every one in his meaſure? And do you finde it in your <hi>Form,</hi> where you ſtick? If not, minde the footſteps of the Flock, and which way God hath led them, and where he feeds his Lambs; and minde that which leads them, and muſt lead you into the freſh Paſtures, where they finde food which ſatisfies. Let go your partition Walls, ſo as not to bear up your ſelves in your thoughts above others thereby, (as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did) and come into the unity of the Spirit, where the everlaſting Unity ſtands, and which knits all the members of the body together; and even from the higheſt to the loweſt, though ſcattered in many appearances. So that <hi>our bounds</hi> lye <hi>not in form</hi> but <hi>in the ſpirit,</hi> and where we feel the life. If the Kingdome which you ſeek be not of this world, but of another thats inviſible; if it be within, not
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64127:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>without; then you muſt come to that inward guide, to lead you into that inward and inviſible Kingdom, which leads out of the things that unite you to the world, (namely the luſts of the fleſh, the luſts of the eyes, and the pride of life) and him muſt you follow out of theſe things into the Kingdom. Call that Guide by what name you will, <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> as <hi>Solomon did;</hi> or <hi>the Light</hi> which enlightens every man that comes into the world; or <hi>the Spirit,</hi> or what other name ſoever it is named by in the Scriptures; That you muſt obey and follow out of that which defiles and corrupts, into that which is pure, and holy, and eternal: For without holineſſe no man ſhall ſee God, nor come to have fellowſhip with him.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
